<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Overview</title>
  <author email="dev@commons.apache.org">Commons Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

<section name="The I18n Component">
<p>Developing a localized application is already supported by the Java language in a comfortable way. 
This package adds the feature of localized message bundles that group localized
messages together. Think of a localized error description that consists of title, text, summary and
error details. These localized messages can be grouped together to form a localized error bundle.</p>
<p>This might be very useful in order to display these entries of the error description to the user in different ways. 
In a web based environment it might make sense to format the error title in a different way than the details. When logging
error messages it might be useful to use different log levels for the error summary or the error details.</p>
<p>Localized exceptions make use of this detailed error description. Have a look at the <a href="examples.html">examples</a>
to see localized exception in action.</p>
<p>A <i>MessageManager</i> takes care of handling different pluggable <i>MessageProviders</i> that deal with different
message sources. This allows you to define the messages in your favourite format and 
enables easy migration to the i18n-component.</p>
<p>Each <i>MessageProvider</i> can handle a number of different resources so that a bunch of messages 
defined in a single resource (e.g. a file) can be updated or uninstalled.</p>
<p>To get started go <a href="quickstart.html">here</a>.</p> 
</section>

<section name="Features at a glance">
<ul>
  <li>Messages that are part of an entity can be grouped together using bundles</li>
  <li>The localization takes place lately when accessing message entries. This allows printing the same message in different languages.</li>
  <li>Localized exceptions enable a java applications to provide detailed localized exception messages.</li>
  <li>XML and ResourceBundle based message providers</li>
  <li>Pluggable custom message providers enable access to existing data sources.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section name="Releases">
<p>
None. This is a <i>sandbox</i> component.
</p>
<ul>
  <li>The code is unreleased</li>
  <li>Methods and classes can and will appear and disappear without warning</li>
  <li>If you like the code and want to push it towards a release, join the mailing list!</li>
</ul>
<p>
You can obtain snapshot builds <a href="http://people.apache.org/repository/commons-i18n/distributions/">here</a>.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Documentation">
  <p>
     The <a href="apidocs/index.html">JavaDoc API documents</a> are available online.
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Class diagrams">
  <p>
     For an easy overview there is a <a href="i18n.pdf">class diagram</a> in PDF format.
  </p>
</section>

</body>
</document>